>> Hello everyone, and
welcome to today's webinar.
Before we begin, we want to
cover a few housekeeping items.
For any common technical issues,
please refer to the Help widget
located at the bottom of your screen.
This webinar was pre-recorded and
is being presented with a live Q&A.
If you're tuning in for
the initial webcast,
you can submit questions via
the Q&A widget on the
left side of your screen.
The researchers will
be answering them
via the widget in real time.
Also stick around after the
webinar for the live Q&A,
when the researchers will dive
deeper on popular questions asked.
Additional resources
and links provided from
today's presentation can be found in
the resource list on the
right side of your screen.
An on-demand version
of the webinar will
be available approximately
one day after
the initial webcast and can be
accessed using the same audience link
that was sent to you earlier.
On-demand viewers will get to hear
the recorded version of the live Q&A.
Enjoy the webinar.
>> Hi, I'm Chris Lovett,
and I work in the Microsoft
Research Lab in Redmond.
In this webinar, I'll explain
the Coyote project and walk
through some example code.
Coyote is a .NET Framework and
testing tool that can help
you solve problems with
concurrency and non-determinism in
the state machinery of your code.
This project is brought to
you by these three people:
Pantazis and Akash, and the
code is available on GitHub.
Software developers are struggling to
manage the complexity of their code,
especially as things are becoming
more and more asynchronous.
Also, as we move into the
world of microservices,
engineers are being
asked to ship more
frequently in a world that is
more and more distributed.
At the same time, this
complexity results in more bugs.
As businesses, including Microsoft,
deliver more of their mission
critical systems in the Cloud,
bugs in this code result
in serious revenue loss.
So this makes it even more critical
that we do everything we can
to improve the state of the art
for engineering these systems.
Coyote guides developers
into building rock solid,
highly parallel code.
Let me illustrate.
This animation shows messages passing
through a highly parallel
distributed system.
Each node represents a microservice
or a piece of code
running on some machine.
Messages are flying through
the system in a way that makes
it really hard to debug
when something goes wrong.
Coyote tests one
async path at a time,
exploring all possible
paths through the system,
and it does this very quickly.
It also records this path so
that when it finds a bug,
that bug is a 100
percent reproducible.
That's still pretty abstract,
so let me show you something
that is a real system.
This is an implementation
of a complex fault
tolerant cluster
protocol called Raft.
Here you see five servers in
green all communicating with each
other as they implement the
protocol to elect a cluster leader.
Each server runs in parallel
with respect to the others,
so that the messages are flying
around as you can see here.
As you can imagine, this sort of
thing is really hard to debug.
Coyote can help break
this down into something
that's testable and debuggable.
First, to use the Coyote
framework to declare
your message types and
your state machines,
which are the groups here,
and the states inside each machine.
So we see four states here.
You also declare what are
the valid events that can
be received in each state,
then you write a Coyote test and run
it using the Coyote test tool.
In test mode, Coyote
takes over control
of all concurrency and
non-determinism in
your code and all possible timings
of events in this
asynchronous system.
Let me show you what
that looks like again.
If I play that, you can see it
playing one message at a time.
So Coyote is able to test your system
one message at a time and
visualize the results.
This is one test iteration containing
one specific ordering of thousands
of messages through the system.
In this case, Coyote
found a bug where two of
the servers in this cluster
become the cluster
leader at the same time,
and that's these red nodes here,
which is actually a problem
that violates the protocol.
The really cool thing is that
when Coyote found this bug,
it also recorded the exact message
ordering that was required
to create that bug.
So you can replay the bug instantly
in your debugger and you can
actually debug it without
a million different threads
going on at the same time.
So when you use Coyote to build
these kinds of distributed applications,
you get for free a powerful
testing tool that can
intelligently test your code
and find bugs automatically.
Even better, when Coyote
found a bug like this,
it's also a 100 percent reproducible.
The animation you just saw
is also greatly slowed down,
just so that we can see
what's going on here.
The Coyote tester itself can
run hundreds of these
iterations per second,
making it possible to search
the enormous space of
possibilities to find even
the most difficult bugs.
So this is like a search problem,
and Microsoft Research has provided
some built-in search algorithms to
help narrow down the search for bugs.
These have been tested
and verified with
real customers working
on large code bases.
So who's using Coyote?
Several teams in Azure are using
Coyote to build their
production services already,
including various
teams in Azure Batch,
Azure Blockchain, and Azure Compute.
For example, a team in Azure
Batch is using Coyote to
be able to check the correctness
of their failover logic.
The Azure Batch team has over a
100,000 lines of code
using Coyote framework.
Another team in Azure
Compute used Coyote to help
them move to a much more responsive
and asynchronous design,
which enabled the Coyote lock
free event-based actor
programming model.
They actually got not only
a better system using
Coyote and a system that
could debug more easily,
but their final system actually
performed better as well,
which is really interesting.
All these customers are reporting
significant improvement
to productivity and
confidence that their
systems are ready for
production each time
they make a change.
So Coyote provides two
programming models.
One is based on the
task programming model,
which is built on the .NET
Framework task platform.
The second programming model is
a more advanced actor
programming model,
using events and state machines.
I will show you both of
these programming models
with some examples.
First, the task model.
This programming model offers
a task type that serves as a
drop-in replacement for the native
.NET system threading task.
Tasks represent an
asynchronous operation and
integrates really nicely with the
C# feature, async, and await.
In production, a Coyote task
executes with the same
semantics as the .NET task.
In fact, it's a very thin
wrapper around the native task,
which means it has a very
minimal overhead in production.
During testing, however, is where
the magic happens and
Coyote can take over
the execution of all tasks
during the test and can explore
various different
interleavings between
the scheduling of all those
tasks to help find bugs.
This model is in preview and
is available right now.
So let's take a look at some code
that uses the task programming model.
As is always the tradition
with this sort of thing
is to show the simplest possible
HelloWorldTasks example.
This code is available in GitHub,
so I'm going to go over there.
I have the repo right here
and I'm going to load
"HelloWorldTasks" into Visual Studio.
Here we see a simple
console application
with a program and
a main entry point,
and we see that we have
a class called Greeter.
The Greeter looks like
a normal C# class with
an async method called
WriteWithDelayAsync.
It simply sets a member field
after some delay. There's the setter.
The run async method starts
five separate tasks on purpose
to make them run in parallel,
calling that async method.
Then it uses this
construct here on Task
to wait for all five of
those tasks to complete.
Then it writes out the
final value that was set.
Clearly, this is setting
up a race condition where
the value will be
randomly set to one of
these two different strings
depending on which task
gets scheduled last in
this parallel operation.
So to finish this sample,
we write an Assert here.
In this case, we wrongly
assert that the final value
after running these five tasks
will always be HelloWorld.
Clearly, that's not
always going to be
true because we have one
that sets it to GoodMorning.
So we've injected a bug
into this code on purpose,
and let's run it and
see what happens.
I went ahead and built that
and let me run this version
here in the window.
Right off the bat, it hit the bug,
but let's run it again
and again and again.
You can see it randomly
succeeds or fails depending
on that thread scheduling.
So this is basically the definition
of a non-deterministic bug.
You'll see that the
Coyote website talks
a lot about non-determinism
because that's one of the
things that Coyote can be
really good at helping you test.
So what I'm going to do
is show you how to run
this program in the Coyote test tool.
But before I do that, let me just
show you how that's going to work.
Back in the main program,
you'll see that there's
a Coyote test attribute
on this Execute method.
This test to attribute allows
the Coyote test tool to test this
program in a special test mode.
The Coyote test tool
lives in the Coyote repo.
If you build the Coyote source code,
this is building the Coyote
project from source.
What we'll see is
it's building all of
the Coyote runtime projects here,
including the Coyote test
tool that we're going to
use to test our HelloWorld
application.
There's the Coyote test tool
being built right there.
That's the one we'll use.
Great. Now, we go back
to the samples folder.
We're going to use
that Coyote test tool.
If you just hit enter here,
it shows you all the
command line arguments
that you can pass to this tool,
including what you're testing,
which is passed as an assembly path.
So we're going to test what we
just built in the Bin folder.
We have to pick the same .NET
platform, .NET46, HelloWorldTasks,
and we'll do 100 test iterations
and we'll see if it can find a bug.
So as we expected,
because the bug was
hardcoded into this program,
when we run this in
the Coyote test tool,
we need a bunch of iterations,
which is what I passed in
that command line there.
Then it hits the bug, so it did
seven iterations in this case,
and then it found a bug which
is reported - found one bug.
It provides a log file that
tells you exactly what happened
when that test failed.
So let's look at that, right here.
You can see the log file says
the value was 'Good Morning'
instead of "Hello,"
that's because of the failed assert.
It also gives you the
stack trace of where
that bug was found in your
program, which can be handy.
Now, the interesting thing
is that it also provides
a schedule on how it
created that bug,
and this is where the real
magic happens with Coyote.
What you can do is you can actually,
instead of test, is a search for bugs,
but you can replay that schedule.
Replay will jump straight to the bug.
So you say replay,
I have to give it the schedule,
and instantly it found the bug.
It didn't have to search this time,
it's actually got the bug already.
I can even run that
with a break command,
which will put us on a
breakpoint inside Visual Studio,
and we can start debugging
this thing with 100 percent
certainty that that bug will happen.
So this is really huge,
for those of you who've
spent way too much time
debugging these sorts of
problems with multithreading,
it can be extremely time-consuming.
I've spent days trying to find a
really nasty multithreading bug,
and Coyote actually makes these
things debuggable quickly,
100 percent reproducible, super
useful feature of Coyote.
There are some challenges with tasks,
which I'll walk through here.
Let me go back to Visual Studio.
When you write a bigger program,
like the coffee machine example
that we'll look at in a little bit.
Oftentimes you'll find yourself,
especially if you have a lot
of multithreading going on,
you'll find yourself having to use
the lock statement
with some sort of sync object,
and you now have to protect
the update of local state
from multithreading issues.
Well, the lock statement
is interesting.
If I call out to some other method,
I now have to worry about deadlocks.
If I call a method
and that method
starts another AsyncTask
there and waits for it.
That AsyncTask then calls back into
this object and that tries
to lock, I have a deadlock.
Deadlocks are also
difficult to debug.
The other thing is that when you have
all this Async code
and you need locks,
you can't use the
await keyword inside.
In fact the IntelliSense is
not even letting me
because it's not allowed.
You're not allowed
to use await inside
a lock because that can be
also a guarantee for deadlocks.
So there are some non-trivial
aspects to writing thread
safe code that you run into if you
have a lot of parallel
tasks in your programs.
Deadlocks can't use Async,
and you have to protect your state.
So async methods are a
powerful feature of C#.
Async await is a really cool thing,
but you have to be careful,
there are complications.
So this leads us to
the other programming model
that Coyote provides,
which is an Actor-based
programming model.
There's actually a lot of
computer science research into
Actor programming models that show
some great advantages
of using this model.
The first thing that we do with
Actors is you cannot
call them directly,
you have to send events to them
and that goes through an inbox.
So each Actor has an
inbox, it's kind of like e-mail.
You send a message to
an Actor and you cannot call
methods directly on the Actor.
The only thing you have is an ID,
which is the thing
that you need to send
the message to an Actor,
that's the ActorId.
Think of an Event as
a bundle of method parameters
that are wrapped up in an
object called an Event,
and that's what you
send to the Actor.
But that Event then is
something that can live
outside of any call stack,
unlike method parameters that
are always on a call stack.
An Event can just live
forever in an inbox,
independent of call stacks.
There's a lot of
information on Wikipedia
about this programming model
and how it came about.
It's very popular in the
world of distributed systems.
So Events can also easily be
serialized to create
a distributed system.
So now your Events are actually going
across the wire to other systems.
So what we do with
Actors in Coyote is,
we run each Actor in a
separate thread or task,
but the Actor only dequeues and
processes one Event at a time,
which means the Actor
internal implementation
doesn't need to worry
about multi-threading.
So we don't need to do any locks.
Which is why we said that
Azure Batch got a
performance improvement,
because they were doing lock
free programming, basically,
and the parallelism
happened at a higher level.
Instead of doing parallelism
at the method level,
you're doing it at the Actor level,
that actually greatly simplifies
your programming model.
It's a little bit
similar to ASP.NET that
says you could process one
HTTP request at a time.
Here an Actor processes
one Event at a time,
so it's a lock-free
programming model.
So let's take a look at
the simplest possible Actor
program, HelloWorld.
So again, that's here in
GitHub and we'll load
that into Visual Studio.
HelloWorldActors, right here.
Has a very similar program with
a main entry point
and a Greeter class,
except this time, the
Greeter class is an Actor.
You can see that this Actor
is provided by the
Coyote Actor namespace.
So with Actors, you declare what
types of Events can be received
with a custom attribute.
This says that the Greeter
is expecting to receive
a request for Greetings
in this Event type.
So what we can then do is go
to the definition of an Event.
Event is also provided
by the Coyote namespace,
and here you can put
data inside your Events.
So here we've got one piece
of data that we're sending,
which is the ID of the Caller.
So the Caller is calling the Greeter,
requesting that the
Greeter return a Greeting.
The Greeter will return
this Event down here,
which is another Event which contains
a Greeting just as a string.
So this is how you bundle these
Events into various Event objects,
and you can now send
them to the Actor.
So you declare what type of
Event you can receive or handle.
So this Actor can handle
RequestGreetingEvents,
and this tells Coyote
what method to call when
that Event is received.
So it's going to call
HandleGreeting right here.
We can cast that back to
the type we're expecting.
We can create a Greeting using
a random choice
between "Hello World!"
and "Good Morning". So
this is actually going
to choose randomly between those two.
Random number generation is also
provided by the Actor base class,
because Coyote wants to actually be
involved in the generation of
random numbers at test time.
The Greeter then simply does a Send
Event to send the Greeting
back to the Caller,
which is provided in this Event,
and with a chance of one in 10.
So that's what Random
Boolean(10) means.
A one in 10 chance it's going
to send a second greeting,
and this is our bug in this case,
we're injecting a bug in
here on purpose that sends
too many Greetings
back to the Caller.
So how do you test an Actor?
Over in the program,
we have another class
called a TestActor.
The TestActor is going
to act like a client,
if you like, of the greeter.
So the TestActor has to
create the Greeter and calls
SendEvent requesting a Greeting.
So this is how we test our
Greeter by creating the Actor.
Again, what we get back here is
not an instance of a C# object.
We don't ever have permission to see
the real instance of
this object that's created
by the Coyote runtime.
This ensures proper decoupling
between your various Actors,
and is able to then
guarantee this thread safety
that we talked about,
and that only one message
is handled at a time.
So what I get back is an ActorID.
That ActorID is then what
we use to send an Event.
Here, we're going to send up to
five random number generation,
one plus random to five.
So we should send one to five
messages here to that Greeter,
and we'll store in this
little variable here,
Count how many greetings we sent.
Now, notice that the
TestActor is also an Actor.
So just like the Greeter,
this TestActor tells Coyote with
a custom attribute what kind
of Events it can receive,
which is this GreetingEvent.
When it receives a GreetingEvent,
call the HandleGreeting method.
The HandleGreeting
method is down here.
We're able to cast that
back to GreetingEvent
and we decrement the Count.
So here we're actually going to
start writing some test code.
We will decrement the Count
and print out what
the Greeting was, just so
we can see it in the log,
and we're going to assert that
this Count never becomes negative.
If it does, then we have
a problem that there are too
many Greetings returned.
Of course, we've injected
a bug in here on
purpose that will return
too many Greetings,
and so with a one in 10 chance,
this program should
report that error.
So we go ahead and build that,
and we'll run that version,
and I'll just bring it over
to our Console Window,
run it like this.
When you run a Coyote program like
this outside the Coyote tester,
we call that running in production.
This is exactly what you would
do with a production Coyote program,
you just run it like
any other C# program.
Coyote is just a library that
is loaded in the process.
So we've run it once,
we've run it twice,
this time we've got five Greetings.
So far, we haven't seen that
bug because there's only a
one in 10 chance we'll ever
actually get that bug infect.
There we go, finally. So I had to
run it a lot of times manually.
So this is the thing
with non-determinism,
you'll typically find yourself
having to run a lot of
iterations before you actually
trigger the bug that
you're looking for.
Then when you get the bug,
how do you reproduce it?
It's so hard to reproduce
in the first place.
So let's run this in Coyote,
just like I did with the other one,
we'll run Coyote test.
We have to have the
same .NET platform.
So we'll run the 46 version.
We just ran one iteration,
but let's run 100 iterations.
Whoop! Found the bug
right away in that case.
But let's do it again and again.
You can see it's
finding the bug really
quickly every time I run this.
Again, as before, there's a log file.
This time the log file is a
little bit more interesting,
because it's showing you more of
the Coyote Actor runtime activity,
including messages
when they are sent.
So we can see a whole
bunch of send operations,
and then as the messages get dequeued
and executed by an
action on the Greeter.
So this is the Handle
Greeting action.
Then finally, we see the assert.
Too many greetings returned,
which was triggered by that assert.
Again, we can replay this
as well, just as before,
and we can get the 100
percent reproducible bug.
Now, let's take a look
at a bigger example.
We have the coffee machine example,
where we also have an
asynchronous version of
the coffee machine up here on GitHub
using async tasks right here.
You can look into that
in your own time.
But if you check out the code,
you'll see that the
task-based version
of the coffee machine
is using a lot of locks
and even needs async locks in
order to get its state correct.
The Actor version is
lock-free and that's the one I want
to look at in a little
bit more detail here.
So what is this coffee
machine example about?
The coffee machine example shows
you how to build a state machine.
So Coyote Actors not only
provide an Actor model,
but they provide a first-class
state machine model.
So this is a fun, little coffee
machine that I have in my kitchen,
and that reminds me,
I need some coffee, very good.
It has a state machine.
So what does it do?
That coffee machine, first
of all when you boot it up,
it checks the state of everything.
What's the water level?
What's the coffee level?
It has a water heater, of course,
it's got to heat up its water.
So it can make steam,
and it's monitoring that.
When it's ready, you can press
the make coffee button and it'll
run the grinder which
will grind the beans.
It will then fill up
that little filter thing
that pumps the water through,
starts making shots. The
shots come out at the bottom,
and of course some things can go
wrong, as in always with machines,
so you can run out of water
and a refill is required.
This machine, obviously you need
a manual refilling process
for both the coffee
beans and for water.
Otherwise, if everything's good,
it can clean itself up and
go back to the ready-state.
This is all implemented in
the coffee machine example using
Coyote Actor programming model.
Let's take a look at that in
Visual Studio, CoffeeMachineActors.
All right. So the CoffeeMachineActors
has a CoffeeMachine,
and this is a new concept
in Coyote that I haven't
talked about yet,
which is StateMachines.
A StateMachine in Coyote is
a special type of Actor that
understands all of those states
that you saw in that state diagram.
Now in a StateMachine,
what you do is you declare,
so it's also declarative,
you declare the States
of the machine with
a class that inherits from
the Coyote State base class.
State is a nested class
inside StateMachine.
So this is telling Coyote that
this class has a State
called CheckSensors.
Now remember with regular Actors,
these were all at the class level.
But now with StateMachines,
we can move that down
into the State-level,
so for each State,
you can declare what
Events are valid,
what can you do when
you're in that State.
You can also tell Coyote
to defer certain States.
So don't try to make a coffee
yet because we're not ready.
You can also have a
special Event that
happens when we enter this State.
So this is like a
set-up piece of code
that happens when we enter
the CheckSensor State.
What do we do? Well, what
can we do with Actors?
We can send Events. So what do we do?
We send Events to the CoffeeGrinder,
and we tell it to turn
off the CoffeeGrinder,
we turn off the WaterPump,
we turn off the WaterHeater.
We also send some read Events over to
those various sensors to
read the water level,
read the hopper level,
because we want to make sure the
beginning of this StateMachine
that all the sensors
are in a good State,
that we actually have water, that
we can make coffee and so on.
So since we sent these read requests,
that's why we're getting back
four read responses basically,
these are the four Events
that were expecting back.
These can all happen completely
asynchronously depending
on thread scheduling.
But our code is
handling those Events.
So here's an example of when
we get back the water level,
we handle that right here.
We get a water-level, we store
it in a local member variable,
we print it out and we check to
see if the water level is empty.
If it's empty, then we have
to go to a different State,
and here you can see a more
state machinery showing
up where we tell Coyote that
we're going to transition
to a different State.
This can be done either in
code and it can also
be done declaratively.
I don't think there's an
example of that on here,
but let's see, OnEventGoTo,
there's a declarative way of
saying when the MakeCoffee,
if we're in the ready State
and somebody presses,
"The Make Coffee" button, then
we can just go straight
to the MakeCoffee State.
So this is something
that's completely
handled by the Coyote runtime,
we don't even have to
write any code to do
that State transition
to making coffee,
and then when we start making coffee,
that's when the really
interesting stuff happens,
we grind the beans,
we go into GrindingBeans
State and so on and so forth.
So you can see how
that StateMachine is
progressing throughout
this code here.
The sensors then is,
this is called MockSensors because
this is not the real machine.
Obviously, this is not the actual
firmware of the real machine.
This is built just for testing.
We have Monitors, which I'll
get into in a little bit,
but we have the door sensor,
we have the water tank,
and these are all just simple Actors.
These are simple
enough that it didn't
need to use the StateMachine model,
it can just be a simple Actor.
So the water tank can register
a client that it can talk to.
It can read the water level,
as you saw earlier.
It can read the water temperature,
you can actually turn
on the water heater,
and there's a timer concept.
So Coyote Actors also support Timers,
which is a frequent callback Event
that can happen automatically.
Then you can pump the water
to make a coffee and
so on and so forth.
There's another Timer involved there.
So this is an example of a mock
implementation of an Actor that's
implementing the logic behind
the sensors and the hardware
of the coffee machine.
The CoffeeMachine
class then is more like
the CPU of the coffee machine,
it's the thing that
coordinates all that
hardware and makes the
machine actually work.
Now, up a level here we
have a Failover driver.
So this sample is more
than just showing you
how state machines work.
This sample is going to do one
more really interesting thing.
To test that our code is
ready for prime time,
we're going to reboot
the coffee machine.
So imagine if the
little tiny CPU inside
the coffee machine glitched out and
rebooted halfway through
making a coffee.
What bad things could
happen with that?
Obviously, if you're not careful
in how you write that code,
it could do all kinds
of silly things.
Then what we do is we have
some assertions in the code,
things that we want to
verify, never happen.
For example, do not turn on the
water heater if there's no water,
bad things could happen, it
can burn down your house.
Do not turn on
the coffee grinder if there's
no beans in the hopper,
that can ruin the grinder.
Don't try to make a shot if
there's no water and so on.
There's also a safety feature.
If the door is opened,
the machine has to not do anything,
you don't want fingers
getting stuck in there.
So these are safety asserts
that you'll see throughout
the sample code and
shows how Coyote can help ensure that
these asserts are always
true during testing,
even during failover testing.
So we're going to boot
up one coffee machine,
it's going to get halfway through
it's process
and then we're going to
kill it, just like that,
and then we're going to start
another coffee machine,
and what this test is
proving is that the code is
hardened to handle failover nicely.
The new coffee machine,
when it boots up,
needs to verify all
of the sensor states,
relearn what's happening,
and make sure it doesn't
do something silly.
When you build this program,
it's still just a very
simple console program,
and we get this here,
and there'll be a bunch
of print statements that
show you what the coffee
machine is doing.
If we run that over here,
right off the bat is we can
see that it detected
that the door was open,
great, so the door was open,
which we can see in
red, the mock sensors,
because those are test classes,
do actually initialize the
machine with random states.
So the door sensor,
it randomly chooses
to be open or not.
The water levels are randomly set
and the temperatures are set,
the coffee levels are random,
and that also helps the testing of
this program discover more
of these fault cases.
So that was interesting. We hit
the error case right off the bat.
This time it's off and making coffee.
However, we started off with
random water levels and coffee
levels that were very low.
These are very low numbers.
It did heat up that water,
which is fun, and it
started making coffee.
So it started grinding beans
and started filling
up the porter filter,
but then it ran out of coffee
beans halfway through.
So automatically it
went to an error state,
at that point, the
coffee machine is done,
there's nothing more that you can
do with this test without restarting
the test until we manually
refill the coffee machine.
Let's see if we can find
a run that actually
goes all the way to making coffee.
No, that one's empty and
this one looks good.
It's got higher levels there,
so it's making shots and it
makes the coffee, great,
all the way to three shots completed.
So the first round of running
that coffee machine worked.
Now remember all the
events flying around
between the coffee machine and
those mock sensor hardware
objects are all asynchronous.
So this is a very
asynchronous program.
So it will keep running until
it runs out of resources.
But the question now is,
how can we test every
possible interleaving of all
of those Events and see if
there are any bugs in the code.
We actually did inject a bug in the
code and we haven't hit it yet.
In fact, you can run it like
this all day long and you'll
probably never hit the bug that
we've injected in the code.
So again, we'll run
this in the Coyote test
tool to see what happens.
Coyote test tool has some more
options besides iterations.
I can also tell it, "What
are the max steps?"
So for each iteration
you can explore it,
but what if your program is
just an infinite program?
You have to tell it to
stop somewhere, otherwise,
the Coyote test tool will
just get stuck in exploring
an infinite state of transitions.
So what you can do is
you can say max steps,
and let's say max steps is 500.
There's no point testing
more than 500 events at a
time for each iteration.
You can also use different
scheduling algorithms.
So Coyote, remember I said that
Microsoft Researchers built a bunch
of different search algorithms,
and you can actually specify
the search algorithm that
you want to use in a test,
and this is called PCT.
There's a lot more
documentation on that online,
what that means, but I'll
go ahead and run that.
So here it is setting up everything,
iteration 1, 2, 3,
4, and it found a bug.
All right, surprise, surprise, I know,
we put it in on purpose.
Let's take a look at the log file,
and now this is more interesting.
This is a real system, this
is not just Hello World,
and so what we see now
as I page down here
is 600 events before
we found the bug,
and this was an assert
that triggered that said,
"Please do not turn on
the grinder if there's
no beans in the hopper."
So with this failover experiment
where we killed one machine,
started another machine,
we're making coffee
all throughout this,
we actually found a bug where it
did try to turn on the grinder
when there were no beans.
So there's definitely a bug in here.
So the fun part of this exercise
then is to try to find that bug.
I'll let you do that
in your own time.
The other thing you can do with
this test is you can ask for graph.
Now I'm going to ask for graph of
just the one iteration
that contained the bug
and because of all of that
declarative state machinery
around States and Events that
can be received and so on,
there's a very cool feature
that's provided by Coyote
which is producing a DGML diagram.
DGML can be visualized
using Visual Studio.
So here we go. This is
a visualization of all the States
and State transitions that happened.
I'm going to press, "Ctrl A" to
see everything that happened here.
All of these links that are
connecting these nodes are
messages that flowed across
these actors in State machines.
You can see that a coffee
machine was created here,
number 5, and it went all
the way through making,
grinding, making shots,
and cleaning up.
So this actually completed the
full iteration of making coffee.
Then it was halted by
the failover driver.
Remember we said we're going
to kill the coffee machines,
here we've killed the coffee
machine and we create a new one.
The new coffee machines
started up and
went all the way through
to grinding beans,
where it hit the assert that said,
"Hey, hang on, there's
no beans in the hopper."
So that's the bug.
It should never have gone that far,
it should have got to check sensors,
and check sensors
should have said, "Hey,
there's no coffee beans,
so what happened?"
But this helps us visualize
what's going on here.
In fact, the diagram animation
that I showed you on
the webpage with the raft protocol
was built from these diagrams.
So this is also a super useful way to
just look at the design of
your program to communicate
that design to other
people on the team and
to visually see what's going
on in a complex system,
which can also be very useful.
So you can see now that Coyote
is more than a test tool.
It's a test tool that integrates
with your development
process by providing
frameworks and declarative ways
of declaring states and so on,
and it integrates with your design
process in the sense that you can
now see what your program is
doing and reason about it.
I glossed over quickly in
that state machine example,
there is also a Monitor.
The Monitor is a type of
state machine that is
a passive listener in a sense
that a Monitor can receive
Events but it shouldn't
be sending Events to
other parts of the system,
so it's just there.
Oftentimes you'll run Monitors
only in test time and not
a production time and
if you don't want
the overhead of monitoring stuff.
The Monitor is something
that Coyote also supports
some really cool concepts
including a LivenessMonitor,
and let me show you
the code for that.
We have a LivenessMonitor
in the coffee machine.
What does that mean?
What are we looking
for with a LivenessMonitor?
A LivenessMonitor is something that
has Cold States and Hot States.
These are two custom
attributes that are
only available on monitors.
Coyote will make sure
that your Monitor doesn't
get stuck in the Hot State.
What this means, the way this can
be used in the coffee machine,
is we're trying to verify
that the coffee machine
always gets the job done.
With async programs,
where you can easily get
stuck in these circular Events storms,
in this case, sends an
Event, which sends an Event,
which sends an Event and you
get this big ladder effect,
it's sometimes hard to
prove that your program's ever
actually going to finish.
I've actually seen this
problem happen with
real commercial large systems where
they get stuck in Events storms
and then never finish the job.
So it's a hard problem.
So the LivenessMonitor is a
tool that you can use with
Coyote to verify that your
machine always finishes the job.
It has to either make
the coffee or report an error
that it needs refilling,
but it should never get stuck in
some intermediate state of just
going round and round and round.
Coyote will actually verify
this at test time and
it has an algorithm that determines
if it's spent too much
time in a Hot State,
Coyote will raise an assert
automatically saying,
''Hey, you've got a problem.''
The door safety Monitor is a
different kind of Monitor.
It's not a LivenessMonitor,
so it doesn't use
Hot and Cold States.
Instead it's just a
global thing that's
monitoring BusyEvents from
the coffee machine and
the DoorOpenEvent.
So it remembers if there's
a DoorOpenEvent that we
should go to the Error State.
When we're in the Error State,
if we ever get any indication
from the coffee machine
that is doing something,
then it shouldn't be,
and that's an error.
So we can assert right off the bat.
If the coffee machine started doing
something while the door was
open, this should never happen.
So that's another way of
writing Monitors using Coyote.
You can run them at test time or
some people actually do choose to
run Monitors in production
as well. All right.
So now, let's move it up
a level to something even
more real and this is the original
example that I showed you,
which is the implementation
of the Raft cluster protocol.
Raft is often used for
fault tolerant clusters.
So what we've done in this
example called CloudMessaging,
is we've provided four
projects that use Coyote.
Since we're on this page,
I'll take the opportunity to show
a classic state machine here,
all implemented with States.
So now with a really clear
glance at this code,
you can see the kind of
state machinery that's
going on in this class.
You don't have to reverse
engineer by looking at all
the member variables and
how those member variables are
sprinkled around all of your code.
It's very clear declaration
of a state machine.
So the four projects in the solution,
the Raft project over here,
is just a C# library
that uses Coyote,
doesn't know anything about Azure,
it's a pure implementation
of the Raft server protocol,
so that's what this class is.
The Raft server is a StateMachine.
But again, like I said, this
doesn't know anything about Azure,
it sends messages and
receives messages and
implements the Raft protocol,
you can see there's quite
a lot of code here.
There's a really great website online
that explains the Raft protocol,
how it works, it's quite intricate.
Of course, if you're building
a fault tolerant cluster
of services, you really
want to know that
that code is correct, so that's
why it's really important
to test this with Coyote.
How do servers talk to other servers?
So in a true distributed system,
you're going to have
some sort of message bus,
some messaging system
that send messages across machines.
Now, Coyote is not in
the business of providing
a messaging platform.
Coyote is not one of those things,
it doesn't compete
with service bus and
compete with any messaging system.
Coyote is just an
abstraction on top of that.
So what we've done here,
is we've modeled the cluster concept,
the Pub-sub concept, if you like.
So a server can send a message to
all the other servers
is a Pub-sub concept.
We've modeled that as a
state machine using Coyote.
So we've created this
cluster manager,
but this is going to be an abstract
class with no implementations.
You can see here that it doesn't
actually implement anything.
It's expected that either
your test will implement
something or your true
Azure deployment will plug
in here how to broadcast a request
across that Pub-sub system.
In the Raft Azure project,
you'll actually see an Azure
Cluster Manager that's
implemented using the service
bus topic client API.
So if you're familiar
with Azure Service Bus,
it provides a concept of Topics.
Topics are Pub-sub concept where
you have a Topic client that can
send messages and you
have a Topic receiver,
a message receiver from
the service bus that can
receive those Pub-sub messages.
So this is how we've plugged
into the Azure Service Bus.
When we receive messages,
we can see we have to parse JSON and
all that stuff Coyote
doesn't care about.
What really matters is at some point,
you get the Coyote Actor runtime
and you call SendEvent.
So there we've gone from SendEvent,
out to a Pub-sub system,
the Pub-sub system has
brought that message back in,
and then we push it back into
the Coyote world, if you like.
So we've plugged Azure back
into this Coyote world.
But we've kept at a
very clean separation.
The reason why that clean
separation is good,
is when you get to the
mocking version of
this program where we
want to test this thing.
So the mock version has
a mock client that sends
Events to the servers,
so this is how we request work
to be done by that cluster.
We have a mock cluster manager
that doesn't know about
Azure Service Bus,
so broadcast is a very simple
for-loop over a list of servers,
where that list of servers
is a bunch of ActorIDs.
So it's a for-loop, just send it to
all the other guys except for us,
the guy who is sending this request.
So the mock implementation
of cluster manager all runs
locally in the same process
even or if you run it locally,
you can run it in multiple processes.
But this one is
actually going to run the
whole test in one process,
which means that Coyote can
run really, really fast.
When Coyote is testing
this Raft protocol,
it doesn't have to wait
for service bus events,
it can run thousands of times
faster in memory on one machine.
It's also super convenient
for a developer
to be able to test
all of their code in
isolation on one machine
before they try to push
it into production.
So let's go ahead and build that.
I won't run the Azure
version because that needs
a Service Bus account
setup and all that stuff.
You can see there's
a setup script that
will do that in the tutorial.
You're certainly welcome
to go ahead and run that,
prove that it works with
Azure Service Bus, provide
connection strings on a
command line and so forth.
But what I'm going to run is
the Mock version of this and
see if it can find any bugs.
This is actually a picture
that after I ran this,
I was using the same
graphing capability
to look at what happened in the
state machine at test time.
So here you can see this is
actually a different type of graph
that's called a coverage graph,
so it doesn't show all
five servers, instead,
it collapses each instance
into one group to just
show you a code coverage.
So it's showing you what are all
the things that happened across
all 100 or 1,000
iterations for testing
this thing and I'll show you
how that works right here.
So I'm going to run the same Coyote
test tool, except this time,
I'm going to use .NET47,
we can also support .NET Core,
which means Coyote is
also a cross-platform,
you can run that on any system
that has .NET Core.
I'm going to test the
bin\net47\Raft.Mocking.dll.
Now, I'm going to test
1,000 iterations, well,
let's do 100 iterations
with Max steps
of 200 steps per iteration
and I'm going to
request that coverage graph
and that's activity coverage.
So this is different
from code coverage,
it's a higher-level
concept of coverage,
which is at that Event level
where all the Events that were
declared Sent and Received by
all the various places that
said they could receive Events,
so it's like an Event coverage graph.
So it went ahead and
it ran 100 iterations,
didn't find any bugs in this
case, which is expected,
because we didn't put
any bugs in it yet.
There's your diagram and
very similar to the
version we saw before.
Let me get rid of that.
"Ctrl A" I can see Events were
sent across these things,
so there's an Event here,
a state machine timer
sent a timer-lapsed event,
the cluster manager
sent Events, and so on.
So the implementation of the
Raft protocol does, in fact,
involve these four states and you
can read about what those states
mean on the webpage
description of this tutorial,
but you can see it's actually
reaching all the states.
Most importantly, for this test,
we want to see that
one of the servers at
some point reached
the leader state and
this can also be a
Liveness problem if
no server has ever
reached the leader state,
then it means they're just jostling
and jostling and jostling for leader,
but nobody's actually getting it.
That would be a Liveness
problem with your cluster,
so it's great to see that during
this test the leader state
was achieved. All right.
So remember, Coyote can help
you with non-determinism.
So we have a fourth
project in that solution,
which is called Raft Non-determinism,
where we can actually start to
model some
non-deterministic behavior.
So oftentimes, when you
build a mock using Coyote,
what you want to do is capture
some of the weird behaviors of
some external system that you
have to deal with. In this case,
we have modeled a situation where
the non-deterministic
behavior is that
somewhere in our messaging system,
whatever messaging system that is,
we end up getting duplicate Events.
Another thing you might model is
Events get lost and
never get delivered.
But in this case,
we're going to model
the non-deterministic problem
that we're struggling with,
is our system can't handle it
when we get duplicate Events.
So let's take a look at
that code just quickly.
The way we do that in
Raft.Nondeterminism is
we inject a special
implementation of
the cluster manager,
where that cluster
manager is going to
randomly decide based on
this random boolean to
send an Event twice,
so we get duplicates.
What's that going to do
to the server and is
the implementation
or the Raft protocol
going to be able to handle
that without any problems.
We can run Raft.Nondeterminism,
just like before,
like that, and it's going to
go ahead and search for bugs.
We've asked for 100 iterations
and we'll see what happens.
Didn't find any bugs,
found zero bugs,
so what I happen to
know is that this bug
is particularly hard to reproduce.
In other words, the
servers are quite good,
the server implementation
is really good.
But I guarantee you,
there is a bug in there, so now I'm
going to show you another
feature of Coyote,
which is that you can also ask
for a whole collection of
different scheduling algorithms,
remember those search
algorithms portfolio.
So this is telling Coyote,
don't just use one
scheduling algorithm,
but throw lots of
different scheduling algorithms
at this problem and, even better,
let's run eight tests at once in
parallel, in different processes.
So this is going to fire
up eight processes on
my box and it's probably going
to kill my poor little laptop,
let's see what happens, and it's going
to give each one of those processes
a different random
scheduling algorithm
and then we're going to search.
So here we can see it
launching all five of
those processes and
it starts firing up,
it's got probabilistic,
it's got random,
fair PCT, so there's
your random selection of
search algorithms if you like.
Off it goes, running, running,
running and it found no bugs.
But the cool thing is,
with these really hard bugs,
I can increase the
max steps and I can
increase the number of iterations.
Coyote is doing all
the hard work for me,
I can run a million iterations
and go have a coffee
and then come back and I got
the bug. Then I can tell
my manager how wonderful I am
that I can find bugs like that.
It'll help your career. I'll let
that run off in the background
and we'll come back and check
it later and see if it found a bug.
So that's the end of my talk
and what we really want
is your input on this.
I think you'll agree
so far that Coyote is
a powerful tool that can help you
grapple with concurrency
in non-determinism.
It's available now both as
a NuGet package and a
source code on GitHub.
If you go up there and
take a look at the website,
you'll see that there are more
examples as well. Like this one,
robots. So if that's your fun topic,
there's a really fun tutorial
here that will show you how
we've used Coyote to help a
robot navigate around a room.
So that thing was running
in the background and
it found a bug and we can
see that there's a log file.
This log file now is huge,
it contains 6,700 Events and
it found a bug and the
bug is that there was
more than one leader elected
in the cluster at one time,
which breaks the protocol.
You can't have a
fault-tolerant cluster if
two servers are competing
for the same job.
So there you see it,
found a bug and we also see
the replayable schedule.
So again, now in a real system,
the replay feature becomes huge.
So it took a long time
to find this bug
but when I replay this using
that replace schedule,
using the replay command,
it'll only have to run
those 6,000 messages.
So it should be a lot quicker
than it was the first time,
so it took 14 seconds the first time,
the replay should be a lot quicker.
Of course, with the replay I
can put that in the debugger,
I can put breakpoints everywhere,
I can step through it
as slowly as I want,
I don't need to care about
that interfering with the
timing of everything.
It will reproduce the bug 100 percent
guaranteed and you can
find the bug and fix it.
We'll try to answer your questions
and issues as quickly as we
can if you post them up on
the GitHub issues list.
We also have a Gitter account
there for Coyote and
the stack overflow tag.
So feel free, post
your questions there
and we look forward to hearing
from you. Thank you very much.